<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Retrospective | Alexander Beletsky's development blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://beletsky.net/blog/categories/retrospective/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://beletsky.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-01T15:28:25+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://beletsky.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alexander Beletsky]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[alexander.beletsky@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Looking back to 2012]]></title>
    <link href="http://beletsky.net/2013/01/looking-back-to-2012.html"/>
    <updated>2013-01-05T17:25:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://beletsky.net/2013/01/looking-back-to-2012</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
    <p>        It's the first Saturday of New Year, so it would be good idea to spend some time thinking of year that passed.<br />
    </p>    <h2>Work in e-conomic</h2>    <p>        That was yet another great year in e-conomic. We have build great app - <a href="https://debitoor.com/">Debitoor</a>. Along the way, we were trying different approaches, re-writing things from scratch, designing and re-designing again and again. Finally we got very solid application built upon Node.js, MongoDB and Backbone.js. Debitoor has been created with scalability in mind, we started with Heroku cloud service, eventually moved to Amazon EC for back-end and Amazon Cloud Front for front-end. Now, it's working amazingly fast and for 8 month we gathered ~20,000 signups, launched service for many countries.<br />
    <!-- more -->
    </p>    <p>        At the beginning of the year we were a bunch of .NET developers diving into JavaScript. Having a very strong team of responsible professionals we've gathered initial knowledge quite fast. I've been focused almost at front-end this year. You probably noticed that I slowed down my writings about <a href="http://www.beletsky.net/search/label/asp.net">ASP.NET MVC</a> and doing more for <a href="http://www.beletsky.net/search/label/Backbone.js">Backbone.js</a>. That just reflects the fact of my current specialization. Initially, I was not very serious about Node.js platform. But with time, I became to love it. It speed up our development velocity several times, the API we've built on this platform shows amazing performance indicators.<br />
    </p>    <p>        The team has been expanded a bit. We got new very strong PO and few developers both in Ukraine and Denmark and all of those guys are awesome. I enjoy friendly and cooperative environment we have in team. Besides of that, this year we got 2 QA guys. QA influenced the development really much and helped to improve overall quality of service. I would also mention amazing UX team we have, calling themselves "UX Wizards Team" I have to admit - we are really doing magically things. UI/UX of app is changing all the time and with each iteration it became more intuitive, comprehensive and good looking.<br />
    </p>    <h2>Speaking and blogging</h2>    <p>        For 2012 and have written 63 blog posts on various topics, primarily on .NET, JavaScript and TDD. Some stats, from Google Analytics:<br />
    </p>    <p>        I don't track GA stats actively and I was really surprised to see the figures. I got 105,490 visits, 79,445 unique visits. That gives 288% more traffic than <a href="http://www.beletsky.net/2011/12/retrospective-2011.html">2011</a>. That's quite big number and I could only hope that this year the traffic would only grow up.<br />
    </p>    <p>        As for most viewed blog posts:<br />
    </p>    <ul>        <li><a href="http://www.beletsky.net/2012/04/new-in-aspnet-mvc4-razor-changes.html">New in ASP.NET MVC4: Razor changes</a> where I highlighted some new stuff of ASP.NET MVC 4 and it's been tweeted by <a href="http://weblogs.asp.net/scottgu/">@scottgu</a> (what explains it's popularity).</li>
        <li><a href="http://www.beletsky.net/2012/02/new-tools-in-my-tdd-arsenal.html">New Tools in My TDD Arsenal</a> I posted about stuff I used in .NET development like NCrunch, NSubstitute and FluentAssertions.<br />
        </li>
        <li><a href="http://www.beletsky.net/2012/06/starting-up-nodejs-development-on.html">Starting Up Node.js Development on Windows</a> as quick introduction to setup Node.js development environment on Windows box.</li>
    </ul>    <p>        Something that I personally liked the most:<br />
    </p>    <ul>        <li><a href="http://www.beletsky.net/2012/01/convention-based-ioc-configuration.html">Convention based IoC configuration</a> convention over configuration principles applied to IoC.</li>
        <li><a href="http://www.beletsky.net/2012/06/7-weeks-with-python.html">7 Weeks With Python</a> my little journey with Python language during Audacity CS101 course.</li>
        <li><a href="http://www.beletsky.net/2012/08/developing-web-applications-faster.html">Developing Web Applications Faster</a> that shows how to apply LiveReload technique to working faster with front-end tasks.<br />
        </li>
    </ul>    <p>        As I said above my focus moved from .NET to JavaScript a bit. I've started a series of blog posts called <a href="http://www.beletsky.net/search/label/BabyStepsBackbone">Baby steps to Backbone.js</a>, I'm learning JavaScript and other front-end frameworks, so I would say more info about JavaScript to come.<br />
    </p>    <p>        As for speaking, I've prepared 10 <a href="https://speakerdeck.com/alexanderbeletsky">presentations</a> during 2012 and had nearly 15 speeches on different events. That's not a lot, but it's much more that 2011 and I feel good about it.<br />
    </p>    <h2>Trainings and Consulting</h2>    <p>        Our <a href="http://xpinjection.com/trainings/tdd-in-net/">TDD in .NET</a> training became very popular. We did a quite of the through the year. It goes very fine and thanks to <a href="http://xpinjection.com/">XP Injection</a> efforts I could only predict more to come. I also did a training on <a href="">ASP.NET MVC</a> which went quite fine, but very small demand could be seen on that. I hope that 2013 will bring some more trainings in JavaScript as well.<br />
    </p>    <p>        In 2012 I've tried myself as a consultant. I've been contacted by the guy who listened to my <a href="https://speakerdeck.com/alexanderbeletsky/large-scale-javascript-applications">JavaScript talk</a> and asked to help with architectural advices on new service he tries to build. I think that was very good experience for both of us. Of cause, that's just a tiny job but I hope that consulting could work for me in future.<br />
    </p>    <p>        I believe that 2012 was just the beginning of Trainings & Consulting part of my duties and 2013 will be the one to prove it.<br />
    </p>    <h2>Communities</h2>    <p>        <a href="http://www.facebook.com/groups/574355212591240/">Kyiv Beer'N'Code</a> is something that I personally happy about. Being relauched in September 2012, we haven't missed any meet up. Taking into account it's bi-weekly meetings that's a lot. New guys, who joined the group are open minded and smart, so it's always interesting to spend time there. I would like to have say big thanks to <a href="">Ciklum</a> company, who provides a support for us.<br />
    </p>    <p>        <a href="http://xpinjection.com/uadevclub/">UA Dev Club</a> is growing and growing. Each meeting gathers more and people and it's great. I did a few talks there I try to attend as more meetings as I can (even if they are talking about Java). UA Dev Club became very active this year and I wish it only improves in 2013.<br />
    </p>    <p>        <a href="http://kievalt.net/">Kiev ALT.NET</a> in opposite a little slowed down this year. Primarily, because it's leader moved to another city, so it became difficult to manage the stuff. Nevertheless, we've organized very cool meetup at the end of year with Jimmy Bogard and it motivated us to go on. We already have planned few meetings ahead and expecting more interesting foreign guests to come. Besides of that, <a href="http://www.jetbrains.com/">JetBrains</a> might be the one who can help us this year.<br />
    </p>    <h2>Side projects</h2>    <p>        The last topic in my list that makes me a bit sad. I have to admit, I haven't produced anything really noticeable through the year. My problem is that I'm starting few projects and none of them could make done. Simply lacking the energy and motivation to accomplish it. I believe that "Less is more" should be my slogan for 2013.<br />
    </p>    <p>        Some new projects appeared in my github profile in 2012:<br />
    </p>    <ul>        <li><a href="https://github.com/alexanderbeletsky/wonka">Wonka</a> - supposed to be a blogging engine based on github with easy integration to ASP.NET MVC applications. I had some designs and ideas of implementing it, but it's still in very early stage.</li>
        <li><a href="https://github.com/alexanderbeletsky/aspnet.mobile">ASP.NET Mobile</a> - small project that I've completed during preparation to the conference. It launched on AppHabor at <a href="http://aspnetmobile.apphb.com/">http://aspnetmobile.apphb.com/</a>, but the traffic is very low there.<br />
        </li>
        <li><a href="https://github.com/alexanderbeletsky/foundstyles">FoundStyles</a> - while my playing with Foundation framework I've decided to build small site to keep gallery of themes there, so <a href="http://foundstyles.com/">http://foundstyles.com/</a> was born. I've created only 3 and after left it. But, currently it has about 300 visits per day and it make sense to update the project. It would be easier, since Foundation moved to SASS.</li>
        <li><a href="https://github.com/alexanderbeletsky/freeze">Freeze</a> - small utility project to make a snapshots of dynamic web sites. Originally I've created it to make a snapshot of Kyiv Beer && Code site and place it to github. I've spent some time on that and it's not yet done (as well as Kyiv Beer && Code site is not moved).</li>
        <li><a href="https://github.com/alexanderbeletsky/github-fs.net">GithubFS.net</a> - using Github remote repository as local file system project. It's on really early development stage, but has some documentation describing ideas. And, it's not done as well.</li>
        <li><a href="https://github.com/alexanderbeletsky/benchmark-js">Benchmark-js</a> - tiny library for measuring JS execution time and putting that to log. Works both Node.js and browser.</li>
        <li><a href="https://github.com/alexanderbeletsky/backbone.computedfields">Backbone Computed.Fields</a> - something that I personally happy with. Started as some code I've created for debitoor it moved as stand alone Backbone.js plugin.</li>
    </ul>    <p>        If you reading this and those projects looks interesting to you, so you would like to pick that up - please let me know.<br />
    </p>    <p>        Something that I has started in 2011 and feel most shame for is <a href="https://github.com/alexanderbeletsky/candidate">Candidate</a>. Being <a href="http://www.beletsky.net/2012/08/re-thinking-candidate-application.html">restarted</a> this year I had big ambitions to actually make it done. I still want to implement some meaningful product for .NET web applications deployment. And Candidate would probably be my focus at the beginning of 2013.<br />
    </p>    <h2>Conclusions</h2>    <p>        Despite of side-projects failure, 2012 was a good year. 2013 is the year of Python that means it would bring happy coding time for all the developers. Happy New Year!<br />
    </p></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Retrospective 2011]]></title>
    <link href="http://beletsky.net/2011/12/retrospective-2011.html"/>
    <updated>2011-12-29T21:37:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://beletsky.net/2011/12/retrospective-2011</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>Last year I failed to create retrospective blog post, so lesson learned and I started a little bit earlier now. Not the 1 day, but 3 days before NY :). Retrospective is a great practice and I hope it give me some value when I'll be reading it next year and laughing on my previous achievements.<br />
</p><p>I'll try to cover 4 basic directions: Career, Development, Blog, Personal.<br />
</p><h2>Career</h2><p>I continue to do my job for <a href="http://e-conomic.com">e-conomic.com</a>. As I said <a href="http://www.beletsky.net/2011/03/my-first-year-in-company.html">here</a> e-conomic is the most important thing that happened to me in 2010 and keeps it influence on 2011. I'm still a product developer there, but in general situation has been changing radically. First of all, we are now much more bigger team. Both Ukranian and Denmark parts of team are growing and new cool guys join us. Second, we finished up few projects at the beginning of the year and joined very cool adventure that I a little described <a href="http://www.beletsky.net/2011/12/why-new-technologies-move-your-product.html">here</a>. Sure, I have fun and boring, easy and tough, nice and bad days there. But overall impression is still very good. As soon as we'll keep same as we are doing, with same level of passion and team atmosphere - we are on right track.  <br />
</p><p>Besides the e-conomic, there is something else that happened to me this year and had direct impact on career - <a href="http://kievalt.net">Kiev ALT.NET</a>. Unfortunately, I did not blog to much about that community just a some <a href="http://www.beletsky.net/2011/12/kiev-altnet-community-thoughts.html">mention</a> here. Community is very important to any developer and I'm really happy I found the one. I haven't noticed how I became a speaker, actually. With a few nervous tries on Kiev ALT.NET I've managed to give up to 8 (or so) public speeches this year. It might not be so much, but great achievement for me. The speaking opened new opportunities, especially in meeting new people. But first of all it is a great joy and motivation to learn new things.<br />
</p><p>With a great atmosphere and enthusiastic people inside <a href="http://kievalt.net">Kiev ALT.NET</a> I've launched another project called <a href="http://kyivbeerncode.org">Kiev Beer && Code</a>. The idea is taken from <a href="http://seattle.beerandcode.org/">Seattle Beer && Code</a> community, but it is nothing more as developers gathering for social coding. The community is very young and to be honest I don't put to much efforts on it's promotion, but it a very beginning. I'm very happy with out current Beer && Code team and will be much more happier if new guys are joining.  <br />
</p><p>I became <a href="http://java.dzone.com/users/alexanderb">MVB</a> (Most Valuable Blogger) for DZone, that I'm really proud for. It is 2-way value, DZone is using my content.. To me it gives additional traffic. I hope we are still partners for long years.<br />
</p><p>At the end of the year I tried myself in completely new area - trainings. Thanks to <a href="http://xpinjection.com/">XP Injection</a> training center in Kiev, I've been invited to 2 days training session "TDD in .NET". It <a href="http://www.beletsky.net/2011/12/xp-days-ukraine-2011.html">appeared</a> so much successful that chief trainer offered me a place in their trainers group. At December 22, I officially <a href="http://xpinjection.com/2011/12/22/beletsky-joined-our-coaches-group/">joined</a> XP Injection. I'm very excited about that and hope I can do my best there. So far, we've planned some further TDD .NET trainings, but definitely TDD won't be the only one topic I can work in.<br />
</p><h2>Development</h2><p>I mean, everything that I work on my own: pet projects, self education etc. I don't remember who said that, but I very agree with this statement - "if you don't write code at home, you are not progressing". You have not time to learn at work. Work is the place to perform. You have to have sharp axe, if you came to chop the wood.<br />
</p><p>My main sharp axe exercise is coding. I try to code as much as I can. For productive coding you have to have some projects. Doesn't matter what exactly, what's important is: you like the idea, you have corresponding technological stack. Technological stack have to correspond the area you want to improve in. My main area's are still: C#, HTML/CSS and JavaScript.<br />
</p><p>I was reading <a href="http://pragprog.com/book/tpp/the-pragmatic-programmer">Pragmatic Programmer</a> this year, with a great advice: "Learn new programming language each year". I formulated Pragmatic Product Developer advice, just for my self: "Release new product each year". Even if you release something at work, release something on your own is completely different feeling. It takes too much effort, it's painful.. But shipment is like drug, you feel very happy as soon you ship.. You fill very bad as you don't ship for a while.<br />
</p><p>While ago I write small article there I <a href="http://www.beletsky.net/2011/09/what-im-going-to-do.html">mentioned</a> what's my targets and what I working on. Let's quickly go through it:<br />
</p><ul><li><br />
<strong>trackyt.net</strong> as I released that late 2010 I did provide a support up the the May of 2011. A lot of new features has been <a href="https://github.com/alexanderbeletsky/trackyt.net">commited</a> there, but still I slowed down the progress much. It has very low traffic, almost 0 active users. I was about to release version 2.0, absolutely different with all good things that I see in GTD. But I have to admit, I failed that. <br />
</li>
<li><br />
<strong>elmah.mvc.controller</strong> <a href="http://www.beletsky.net/2011/03/integrating-elmah-to-aspnet-mvc-in.html">started</a> out as very simple <a href="https://github.com/alexanderbeletsky/elmah.mvc.controller">helper</a> for ASP.NET MVC applications that want to use ELMAH, but with a great surprise to me it appeared so popular, that finally wrapped up in a micro product. Now, it has ~2,000 downloads on <a href="http://nuget.org/packages/Elmah.MVC">NuGet</a>, I've received several pull requests and had a talk about it on Kiev ALT.NET. Even if is so small, I treat that as success. <br />
</li>
<li><br />
<strong>github.commits.widget</strong> also a micro <a href="https://github.com/alexanderbeletsky/github.commits.widget">product</a> that gathered some attention. That was my attempt of working with github API in javascript and I spend maybe 3 hours to create that code, but I know several sites that using that widget. I had joy of creating that and happy that some people find it useful. <br />
</li>
<li><br />
<strong>githubbadges.com</strong> a little <a href="http://githubbadges.com/">application</a> that I wrote to participate <a href="http://10k.aneventapart.com/Entry/Details/512">10K competition</a>. Total application zipped content should not exceed 10K. I've haven't won, I haven't got any mentions.. But again it was fun small project. I used some my knowledge of github API and tried to do very tiny JS and CSS <a href="https://github.com/alexanderbeletsky/10k">code</a>.<br />
</li>
<li><br />
<strong>candidate.net</strong> is something I started this summer of <a href="http://www.beletsky.net/2011/06/candidatenet-application-i-made-on.html">hackthone</a>. Since then I completely rewrite it, start to use <a href="https://github.com/alexanderbeletsky/bounce">bounce</a> framework inside and had plans to release it October, but failed. I'm not throwing away this project and going to ship that soon. I have yet-another-huge-refactoring cycle now, but after that I hope that alpha version could be ready middle January.<br />
</li>
</ul><p>So, it looks like "I did something".. but really nothing impressive. I try to be a little more focused, not more than 2 projects in parallel + very clear criteria's of success for projects. But in general my criteria's are still simple: actually ship it, learn something new, enjoy the ride. <br />
</p><h2>Blog</h2><p>Thanks to google analytics it is very simple to have analysis. Just take a look at those figures: <br />
</p><a href="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-vXQaNQ3spSM/Tvy__2LszrI/AAAAAAAAH2Y/D44-yv0Olpw/s1177/blog-stat-1.jpg"><br />
<img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-vXQaNQ3spSM/Tvy__2LszrI/AAAAAAAAH2Y/D44-yv0Olpw/s1177/blog-stat-1.jpg" alt="stat" style="width: 620px"/><br />
</a><br />
<p>So, I've got 25,341 Unique visitors and 36,560 visits in total. To understand what it means to me, let's take a look last year statistics for same period of time.<br />
</p><a href="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-51Hc2jcZ2rI/TvzAB6TkZJI/AAAAAAAAH2g/26wjbns9Fww/s1179/blog-stat-2.jpg"><br />
<img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-51Hc2jcZ2rI/TvzAB6TkZJI/AAAAAAAAH2g/26wjbns9Fww/s1179/blog-stat-2.jpg" alt="stat" style="width: 620px"/><br />
</a><br />
<p>In 2010 I got 3,979 Unique visitors. It basically means I improved traffic ~637%. This is actually huge number, I don't expect that next year of cause.. but hope that traffic will be improved more. <br />
</p><p>OK, what was most popular content this year:<br />
</p><ul><li><a href="http://www.beletsky.net/2011/03/integrating-elmah-to-aspnet-mvc-in.html">Integrating ELMAH to ASP.NET MVC in right way</a> where I first time described my approach of putting ELMAH into ASP.NET MVC website</li>
<li><br />
<a href="http://www.beletsky.net/2011/01/implementation-of-rest-service-with.html">Implementation of REST service with ASP.NET MVC</a> that I blogged at the very beginning of the year and described my vision on REST services in ASP.NET MVC. With a current experience I would probably change something where, hope to make next popular post.<br />
</li>
<li><br />
<a href="http://www.beletsky.net/2011/10/inside-aspnet-mvc-idependencyresolver.html">Inside ASP.NET MVC: IDependencyResolver - Service locator in MVC</a> one of mine articles of Inside ASP.NET series. It actually became on top of <a href="http://asp.net">http://asp.net</a> website, I was really happy about it.<br />
</li>
<li><br />
<a href="http://www.beletsky.net/2011/06/how-to-start-using-git-in-svn-based.html">How to start using Git in SVN-based organization</a> where I shared some experience of "easy-start" with Git even in SVN based company. It worked so nice to me and my teammates, that almost everyone is using git now.<br />
</li>
<li><br />
<a href="http://www.beletsky.net/2011/03/aspnet-developers-disease.html">ASP.NET developers disease</a> that I wrote under impressions of one of the job interview we did. My main point where was for the guys that stick to much to WebForms and server-side coding. It was a little provocative, but I hope it was useful.<br />
</li>
</ul><h2>Personal<br />
</h2><p>First of all, I got married. I strongly believe it is for good and for long.<br />
</p><p>I did several interesting trips, especially to <a href="http://www.beletsky.net/2011/02/val-gardena-dolomites-trip-2011.html">Val Gardena</a> with my friends at the beginning of the year and <a href="http://www.beletsky.net/2011/11/sayonara-nippon.html">Japan</a>. Unfortunately, I don't predict anything like that in 2012, so it will be kept for good memories.<br />
</p><p>I have to admit I lowered my sport activities too much. I almost stopped every morning exercises, kyokushin karate, rollerblading. Doing those very occasionally. This is not good at all and I already feel bad influence of that. So, my next year is to make it more balanced.<br />
</p><p>It was a great year to me. I wish Merry Christmas and Happy New Year to you, dear reader. I'm really looking forward to create new content you would like, new products you would find useful. Let's gather all good things happened this year and take them for next one.<br />
</p><p>See you 2012!<br />
</p></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
