<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: likeastore | Alexander Beletsky's development blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://beletsky.net/blog/categories/likeastore/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://beletsky.net/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-28T17:14:43+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://beletsky.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alexander Beletsky]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[alexander.beletsky@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lessons Learned Working On Startup]]></title>
    <link href="http://beletsky.net/2014/07/working-on-startup.html"/>
    <updated>2014-07-03T10:41:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://beletsky.net/2014/07/working-on-startup</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last year, July 2013 public version of Likeastore been <a href="http://beletsky.net/2013/07/likeastore-app-goes-to-public.html">released</a>. It gave momentum to change the mind, went out of comfort zone, reconsider priorities and literally change my life. Earlier I <a href="http://beletsky.net/2014/03/from-side-project-to-start.html">blogged</a> about transformation of Likeastore from side project to startup.</p>

<p>Today, I want to share some info on where are we now and lessons I learned so far.</p>

<!-- MORE -->


<h2>Focus on search</h2>

<p>One of the most significant <a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Startup-Owners-Manual-Step-By-Step/dp/0984999302">books</a> on startups, defines startup as temporary organization aims to find sustainable business idea. It&rsquo;s not about coding, testing or anything related to development. It&rsquo;s all about the search.</p>

<p>The biggest mistake of Likeastore, we never did any kind of search before the project started. It was a cool idea that made sense to me and I wanted to make it happen. Development is very expensive process. It&rsquo;s not possible to do good looking and well functioning product without long hours of work. And we worked hard.</p>

<p>Many times I heard opinion <em>&ldquo;work smarter, not harder&rdquo;</em>. That principle transformed to something we know now as <a href="http://theleanstartup.com/">Lean Startup</a>, that basically says <em>&ldquo;do as less as possible before your idea is validated&rdquo;</em>. The only way to validate it is to show it to people and talk to that people after. There is no truth inside the organization, founders might have vision but that vision could be wrong.</p>

<p>Engaging with users, processing the feedback and correction of idea is something that called is Customer Development. Customer Development is vital part of search. Unfortunately, we never accomplish any kind of customer development and currently we suffer that. &ldquo;Likeastore is so cool idea&rdquo; &ndash; we still receiving that kind of emails from our users, that stays for 3 weeks and then slipping away.</p>

<p>Working smarter is hard. For me, that&rsquo;s completely different set of skills and habits. The founder is the one who is able to tweak himself for new conditions and focus on search.</p>

<h2>Coding is easy part</h2>

<p>Being the programmer and spent over 10 years in software development I was sure that I&rsquo;m doing the most complex part of work. All those business guys, product owners and so on, seemed to be auxiliary people, sometimes ones who are just interfere the work.</p>

<p>Working in the company, together with business people, your area of responsibility is primarily the code. But at the end of the day, you don&rsquo;t know what&rsquo;s happening after deployment. How customers work with your code, are they happy.. are they ready to pay the money? Business people care about it and plan on what exactly need to be done further. You turning their ideas into code and get salary not because your code is good, but because business works.</p>

<p>Working in startup is different. No more product owner who says what to do next. You are the product owner. And generating ideas is hard. Talking to customers is hard. Search of product/market fit is hard.</p>

<p>Being able to sit and spend 10 hours for programming is fun for me, but it turned out it&rsquo;s the most easiest part of journey.</p>

<h2>Measure everything</h2>

<p>The code is deployed, some traffic lead to site &ndash; now what? In Likeastore we were blind for quite long time without good understanding of what actually happening inside the application.</p>

<p>The truth is, without data it&rsquo;s not possible to make decisions. We are now utilize <a href="http://mixpanel.com">Mixpanel</a>, <a href="http://www.google.com/analytics/">Google Analytics</a>, <a href="https://github.com/seismolabs/seismo">Seismo</a> custom dashboards etc. in order to understand what&rsquo;s works or not.</p>

<p><em>Build, Measure, Learn</em> &ndash; the mantra of Lean Startup. What we focused on previously is <em>Build</em> part only and that&rsquo;s not right. Startup is ability to make educated guesses, guesses should be based on learnings, learnings are based on measurements.</p>

<p>We are at very stage, but now working hard to create good framework for analytics and measurements.</p>

<h2>Build your own culture</h2>

<p>Even if your are very small, culture plays major role. At the early stage you affect the culture, later stages culture affects you. At Likeastore, we care about marketing and development culture much.</p>

<p>Being based on <a href="http://beletsky.net/2013/12/open-source.html">open source</a> we try to contribute back to open source. I&rsquo;m really happy with our <a href="https://github.com/likeastore">github</a> profile and only predict it&rsquo;s going to grow. We try to open source as much as possible, sometimes even solutions that quite specific to Likeastore.</p>

<p>Our later obsession with metrics and numbers will be part of culture as well. As founder you should see where you want to be in 2-3 years, not only in terms of product, but the way other people know about the company. For me, saying &ldquo;I work on Likeastore&rdquo; means a lot and I want it mean a lot for everyone works here.</p>

<h2>Listen what they say</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s a common practice for business accelerators accepts teams with at least 2-3 founders. I didn&rsquo;t really understand why.</p>

<p>There are few things here. First of all, if you are not able to inspire at least one person with your idea it&rsquo;s likely going to fail. Second, founders should complement each others skills. There are <a href="http://www.marsdd.com/news-and-insights/hacker-hustler-and-designer-building-the-tech-team/">rule of 3</a> that ideal startup team should consists of hacker, hustler, designer.</p>

<p>But there is more important aspect. Founders have to talk all the time, brainstorm and share ideas, discuss competitors etc. You need at least 2 people for discussion. More importantly, you should be able to share your idea with other people. Once we&rsquo;ve <a href="http://beletsky.net/2013/12/likeastore-is-becoming-a-company.html">joined</a> business accelerator, first advice that I received &ndash; &ldquo;talk to other teams, they will help you&rdquo;. I didn&rsquo;t take that advice seriously and I was really wrong. Startups are huge community and you either part of that community or out.</p>

<p>You have to both talk a lot and listen what they say. Co-founders, users, colleagues &ndash; they know something you don&rsquo;t. It doesn&rsquo;t mean you have to do everything they say, but definitely <a href="http://dcurt.is/there-is-no-solution-to-this-problem">listen</a> and analyze.</p>

<p>We are now team of 3 and it feels really good. Each of us have own experience, so we need to combine and make something real out of it. Don&rsquo;t keep secrets, share the stuff. Doesn&rsquo;t matter what exactly your role is, talk to the team, talk to other guys, feel the influence.</p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t close the door of your garage.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Side-Project to Startup in One Year]]></title>
    <link href="http://beletsky.net/2014/03/from-side-project-to-start.html"/>
    <updated>2014-03-31T13:09:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://beletsky.net/2014/03/from-side-project-to-start</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today is exactly <a href="http://beletsky.net/2013/03/likeastore-application-built-on.html">one year</a> as we started <a href="https://likeastore.com">Likeastore</a> project. It went through a different stages, from hack to side-project and finally transformed to real <a href="http://beletsky.net/2013/12/likeastore-is-becoming-a-company.html">startup</a>.</p>

<p>The year, seems to be a huge period of time. It is, but I have to say it&rsquo;s only few last months (from the middle of December till today), we are fully dedicated to project. It&rsquo;s been great ride so far, so I wish to share some interesting moments.</p>

<!--More-->


<h2>What we started with</h2>

<p>Let me remind you, <a href="https://likeastore.com">Likeastore</a> is a web application that allow users to connect their social accounts and collect all their favorite items from them. We are 2 founders, me and <a href="https://twitter.com/voronianski">Dima</a> who committed themselves to build product that matters.</p>

<p>As founders we felt that &ldquo;likes&rdquo; are kind of new way of bookmarking. Then you favorite something on social network you do 2 things &ndash; you send appreciate to author content, as well as marking the content as interesting to you.</p>

<p>The problem that we try to solve. First, there are too many sources of information (social networks) where we spend time and receive content from, so tracking all social likes is extremely difficult. And second, it&rsquo;s very hard to find exact favorite item since social networks provide poor search functionality.</p>

<p>So, our initial hypothesis for application was &ndash; <em>people want to collect their likes in one place and be able to search them</em>.</p>

<h2>Where are we now</h2>

<p>After successful demonstration on hackathon, we&rsquo;ve reimplemented application from scratch and did first private beta in May 2013. It was pretty painful, since after 10 minutes of fly my inbox was full of error messages. But, general impression of people we spoken was positive. We&rsquo;ve crossed the line from hack to side project.</p>

<p>Our public beta released at July 2013. All major issues were solved, the infrastructure established and UI/UX of product were done. We were lucky enough to be featured by Codrops and after by SmashingMagazine twitter, which gave us first 500 beta users.</p>

<p>At the end of 2013 we&rsquo;ve dropped our full time jobs, joined business accelerator and totally focused on a product. I would say, that was the point then we crossed the next line, from side-project to startup.</p>

<p>We are at the full speed, full time, 2 people dedicated to Likeastore. And since then, we did major step forward. Let me share some of current statistics:</p>

<ul>
<li>6.370 <strong>signups</strong> (+ ~4.000 from January till today)</li>
<li>2.700.000 <strong>likes collected</strong> (+ ~1.500.00 from January till today)</li>
<li>~200 <strong>active users</strong> (+185 from January till today)</li>
<li>~600 <strong>feedback emails received</strong></li>
<li>452 <strong>collections created</strong></li>
</ul>


<h2>How does it feel like</h2>

<p>First of all, time flows 2x faster compare to anything I was involved before. You put yourself in a very constraint environment: lack of money, lack of time, not clear whats happens tomorrow. Multitasking is second name of startup, you don&rsquo;t have time to be focused on one task during the day.</p>

<p>Every day you feel ups and downs. The mood is changing constantly. You have growth and receive users feedback &ndash; it feels great. You talk to investors or mentors that find weaks and leaks of idea &ndash; it feels bad. And it&rsquo;s all the time like that.</p>

<p>Founders job here is to supporters to each other, motivate for further wins.</p>

<h2>What we learned so far</h2>

<p><strong> Product / Market Fit </strong> &ndash; basically all you do in startup is finding a balance between value you can propose and market that meets that value. It doesn&rsquo;t matter what the initial idea is, more important is to be able to change direction and put maximum efforts to find the fit. The search could be blind or educated, educated search is probably more successful.</p>

<p>You will never know about that fit, before you try. Almost no idea will survive after it hits the customers. Steve Blanks calls that as &ldquo;getting out of the building&rdquo;, talk to people and show your product before you even built it and spend a lot of money for it.</p>

<p>The product have to solve real customer pain or need to survive.</p>

<p><strong> Metrics are important </strong> &ndash; all decisions have to be taken on metrics. Retention, Cohort analysis, Viral coefficients &ndash; that was all new words for me and only now I realize how metrics are important.</p>

<p>Startup dashboard that aggregates major metrics and KPI&rsquo;s is something that founders spend a lot of time with, finding new strategies and forecasting startup future. Measure everything.</p>

<p><strong> Marketing and Growth </strong> &ndash; current market is already very tight. People are constantly releasing new web and mobile applications, solving different problems, targeting different customer groups. You are a drop of water in the ocean and you have to be noticed to have growth.</p>

<p>I see marketing as car&rsquo;s engine starter &ndash; you built the car, put powerful engine, comfortable chairs and high quality audio system. But without starter, engine won&rsquo;t start and car won&rsquo;t move.</p>

<p>At least basic marketing skills are vital for startup. If founders are more technically oriented (as we are) someone either have to learn it, or you have to hire specialist to help.</p>

<h2>Smooth pivot</h2>

<p>We are growing, average 10% per week. In the same time, we have quite low retention coefficient. People are quite excited about idea of application, but very fast they simply forget about and don&rsquo;t come back.</p>

<p>To be successful on B2C segment, you have to have hundred thousands of users to be sustainable. Likeastore is very far from sustain state as for now.</p>

<p>In the other hand, startup is great place to change your mind. I change my mind all the time. The change of mind in startup have a fancy word for it &ndash; pivot. Pivot is the change of direction that startup does, to find it&rsquo;s product / market fit.</p>

<p>We are going to pivot Likeastore in a very smooth way. As we previously was &ldquo;Dropbox of Likes&rdquo;, just allowing to collect and search.. we now want to try something like &ldquo;Pinterest of Likes&rdquo;, allowing people to collect best content into sharable collections, following that collections and collaborating on them.</p>

<h2>Ultimate goal</h2>

<p>We are putting our bar much higher. Our ultimate goal now is to gather 20.000 users at the end of the May 2014. If it happens, that would mean the idea of Likeastore is alive, otherwise the chances it survives are very low.</p>

<p>Both me and Dima really believe in what we do. We have the vision, will try to turn it to reality and either pivot or try something completely new.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Likeastore is Becoming a Company]]></title>
    <link href="http://beletsky.net/2013/12/likeastore-is-becoming-a-company.html"/>
    <updated>2013-12-16T12:48:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://beletsky.net/2013/12/likeastore-is-becoming-a-company</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s been a while since my last update on <a href="https://likeastore.com/">Likeastore</a> progress. It doesn&rsquo;t mean the application development is stopped, otherwise &ndash; we did a final breakthrough and today is my first day in <a href="http://eastlabs.co/">EastLabs</a> business accelerator. Yes, side project we&rsquo;ve started to have fun on hackathon is becoming a company today.</p>

<p>I always wanted to build a product that could became the foundation for company. I did a few unsuccessful attempts before. There was few reason of failures: either I tried to attack very big problem or I didn&rsquo;t have enough motivation to make the stuff done.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>Likeastore appeared to be different &ndash; first, very positive feedback from out first public release. A lot of people being contacting us, sharing their impressions and asked for additional features. That gave an energy to proceed and improve existing features and design and plan for further grow. And second, I got brilliant co-founder <a href="https://twitter.com/voronianski">@voronianski</a> &ndash; besides great design and coding skills, he shares the passion of Likeastore product, so you don&rsquo;t feel alone in the dark.</p>

<p>Together, we did good team. I knew for sure, that technically we are unstoppable, but product development is not only coding. Realizing that we have a good beginning, very nice potential to grow &ndash; but absolutely not clear where to move on, depressed me a bit.</p>

<p>By the chance, I&rsquo;ve seen <a href="http://www.eventbrite.com/e/kiev-startup-party-tickets-8509553303">Startup Party</a> is taking place in Kiev. And I went there. That was a changing night. I&rsquo;ve met quite few interesting people there who are doing business in Ukraine. I was trying to understand which direction we should go, can someone help us. And of the most realistic ways was to apply to business accelerator. That night I got back home and spend a lot of time reading about business accelerators and options available in Kiev.</p>

<p>We applied to <a href="http://eastlabs.co/">EastLabs</a> accelerator program. We waited long, maybe about a month or so. I even thought, it&rsquo;s not gonna happen, so we need to find out other ways. But finally, we&rsquo;ve received invitation to interview (btw, I wish to say thanks to my friend Yulian who probably triggered that). The interview was really interesting, even if we are not accepted I would treat it as asset. It also took a bit of time from interview, but we finally received an offer from EastLabs to join their program.</p>

<p><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-XS72t-TDB9w/Uq7xtL3JD2I/AAAAAAAAad8/bzEJdq2GZN4/w1736-h1302-no/IMG_20131216_135239.jpg" alt="likeastore"/></p>

<p>Finally, then all cards there on on our hands we needed clearly decide, are we ready to start?</p>

<p>There was a lot doubts.. But there is also one strong feeling &ldquo;Now or never! It&rsquo;s already too late to step back&rdquo;.. We have a chance, now it&rsquo;s our primary job &ndash; not waste it.</p>

<p>So, now with <a href="https://twitter.com/voronianski">@voronianski</a> we are not only developers but also co-founders, ones that are responsible for company grow. That&rsquo;s just a begining of our ride. I only hope it&rsquo;s interesting and fun. For sure, it&rsquo;s gonna be hard, but I&rsquo;m ready to take a challenge.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First Week in The Air]]></title>
    <link href="http://beletsky.net/2013/08/first-week-in-the-air.html"/>
    <updated>2013-08-06T05:40:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://beletsky.net/2013/08/first-week-in-the-air</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s been a week how <a href="https://likeastore.com/">Likeastore</a> application went public. I was amazed with initial reaction and feedback. Right now, we have 730 sign-ups, 844 social networks connected and 117950 likes collected. That mean, we had ~100 signups per day and it&rsquo;s growing.</p>

<p>Here is a little retrospective on the things happened through that seven days.</p>

<!-- More -->


<h2>Few hours after release</h2>

<p>We&rsquo;ve deployed about 6.00 PM at Saturday, sending out a bunch of invitation latters. Right after that, users began to register.</p>

<p>Small script that sends <em>&ldquo;New user registered&rdquo;</em> notification has been rolled out as well, so it was easy to see how things are going. Saturday both me and <a href="https://twitter.com/voronianski">@voronianski</a> were completely tired. No doubt, it has been quite an exhausting journey, we worked hard last 3 weeks at nights and weekends, so I just came home and fall asleep, just checking that application is still running.</p>

<h2>Unpredictable thing</h2>

<p>Next morning, I found a bunch of emails in my box, maybe 40-50 subscribed. Mostly from my &ldquo;nearest&rdquo; network, after notification in twitter and facebook.</p>

<p>But then, something unpredictable happened &ndash; we&rsquo;ve announced in amazing <a href="http://t.co/4DinPVlcdk">Collective #74</a> issue.</p>

<p>That gave us a lot of traffic and sign-ups. Monday and Tuesday, we had a rush hours then every minute new user sign-up. My phone was ringing all the time, and my email box was full of notifications. People were <a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=likeastore&amp;src=typd">tweeting</a> about, we recieved few request for new service connectors as well.</p>

<p>I have to say, I was really pleased with that. We did something noticeable, something that other people liked.</p>

<h2>First problems</h2>

<p>Real user experience shows real application issues. We had few..</p>

<p>First is that our app failed to work in IE. It appeared that our <em>nginx</em> configuration. Since we are using <a href="https://github.com/progrium/dokku">Dokku</a> for deployment, it have to be fixed there. Thanks to Dokku community, the issue has been resolved rather quickly and fix being <a href="https://github.com/progrium/dokku/commit/33a3b85674e92fe883ba3151dee861f53914718a">pushed</a>.</p>

<p>Another thing, that was not possible to see without some <em>real</em> data &ndash; stackoverflow OAuth token is very short living.. So, if you enabled stackoverlow connector, next day it fail to collect the data, since token in not valid any more. Unfortunately, there is no way to workaround this issue automatically, only ask user to re-enable the network.</p>

<p>We had several outages of data collection caused be bugs not noticed on staging. Also, to improve <em>initial collecting velocity</em>, we run 2 instances of collector in parallel. That worked, so just subscribed users are served fast, but it&rsquo;s not ideal yet.</p>

<h2>What&rsquo;s coming?</h2>

<p>The last week was really motivating. We are continue to improve the service and expecting new users to come.</p>

<p>Through the next month we&rsquo;ll be focusing on:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Facebook connector</strong> &ndash; the top most requested connector to be implemented.</li>
<li><strong>Likes indexing</strong> &ndash; currenly implemented search is very simple, just to show the idea, what is really needed is to perform the search based in likes content.</li>
<li><strong>UI improvements</strong> &ndash; we are still improving the design of application, to make it attractive and unique.</li>
<li><strong>Performance</strong> &ndash; our core component <a href="https://github.com/likeastore/collector">collector</a> will be deployed on dedicated core 2 machine and re-written to be easily scaled.</li>
<li><strong>CDN</strong> &ndash; currently all static resources are handled by node.js, which is terrible slow, will move all our stuff to Amazon CloudFront.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Likeastore App Goes to Public]]></title>
    <link href="http://beletsky.net/2013/07/likeastore-app-goes-to-public.html"/>
    <updated>2013-07-28T09:30:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://beletsky.net/2013/07/likeastore-app-goes-to-public</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>About 4 month the project <a href="http://beletsky.net/2013/03/likeastore-application-built-on.html">started</a> on hackathon and called <a href="https://likeastore.com/">Likeastore</a>. Yesterday, it&rsquo;s been pushed out to public and I feel really great about that. Started out as quick hack, it eventually became a real product.</p>

<p>Bootstrapping is always hard, despite of the actual product size. Finishing something that other people will see, just doubles the stake &ndash; you could not fail, wish to do best of the best. It&rsquo;s been really breathtaking journey (or I would call it beginning of the path), so if you are interested I&rsquo;ll share some details of product and it&rsquo;s development.</p>

<!--More-->


<p><img src="/images/blog/likeastore-home.png" alt="likeastore" /></p>

<h2>Likeastore in few simple words</h2>

<p>We all connected to a different social systems, like twitter, github or stackoverlow. All of those are constant flow of information and we clasiffy that information by &ldquo;liking&rdquo; them.</p>

<p>The usual problem though, is it&rsquo;s very hard to remember where you saw some information. For instance, I just remember <em>&ldquo;hm..I read great post of configuring nginx for Node.js application..&rdquo;</em>, but totally forget &ndash; was on github readme, twitted blog post or answer on stackoverflow.</p>

<blockquote><p>Likeastore tool that helps you to survive information overload.</p></blockquote>

<p>Likeastore fixes the problem, it stores all information that you might be interested in, by collecting your &ldquo;likes&rdquo; throught a different social applications and allow you to search that information.</p>

<h2>After hackathon time</h2>

<p>We took a second place on hackathon and a lot of people were interested in Likeastore idea. We just wanted to make it right and enhance the code we already had.</p>

<p>Our plan was simple: make everything we had right, improve the UI and found reliable hosting for our product. As this is done, we go for a private mode, sharing application with limited number of users. If everything is good, will release it public. Pretty standard approach for different kinds of SaaS.</p>

<p>At May, 2013 we had our application deployed on <a href="https://www.appfog.com/">AppFog</a> and subscribers been invited.</p>

<h2>Private beta results</h2>

<p>After few hours on production site running, we&rsquo;ve got first users, first real data and even first feedback in twitter.
But what&rsquo;s more important, we&rsquo;ve got a logs full of errors and understanding we are not that far from previous milestone.</p>

<p>Application stopped to work on next day. We&rsquo;ve <a href="http://beletsky.net/2013/07/why-we-moved-from-appfog-to-nodejitsu.html">moved</a> to another PaaS <a href="https://www.nodejitsu.com/">Nodejitsu</a>. A lot of different things happen.</p>

<p>Looking back, I have to say &ndash; <em>it&rsquo;s great we didn&rsquo;t show it to public immediately</em>, cause it would be a bit shameful. Decrypting the logs, gave us better understanding of problems you face collecting big amount of data through different API&rsquo;s. There was obviously huge amount of work to make it better.</p>

<h2>Focusing on quality</h2>

<p>Originally, we&rsquo;ve planned to push more features to public version: facebook and tumlr connectors, full text search and other stuff. But private beta clearly showed &ndash; the <em>focus have to be on quality</em>.</p>

<p>We literally re-wrote the application from scratch, both server side and client. Applied integration tests and unit tests whereever it&rsquo;s possible, also covering main application pathes with zombie.js <a href="http://pixelhunter.me/post/54753803233/end-to-end-testing-with-zombie-js-mocha-js-and">end-to-end</a> tests.</p>

<p>Our <a href="https://github.com/likeastore/app/tree/master/source/api">API</a> became stable and fully tested, our <a href="https://github.com/likeastore/app/tree/master/public/js">client</a> solid rock and very reliable. The trickiest part of application, the <a href="https://github.com/likeastore/collector">collector</a> &ndash; it became smarter, with a scheduler that schedules optimal requests to avoid API rate limits.</p>

<h2>Making the product beautiful</h2>

<p>Beautiful UI/UX for applications like a crucial. And that&rsquo;s why I&rsquo;m happy that <a href="https://twitter.com/voronianski">@voronianski</a> is a part of team.</p>

<p>He did amazing job by visualizing both site and application. Design became very clean, contrast and looks great on numerous of devices, from smart phones to huge desktop monitors.</p>

<p>Following the modern trend of flat design, we&rsquo;ve picked up colors and styles, showing the way we see application, as modern and useful. Just <em>making the things look nicer</em> would be a real further strategy for us.</p>

<h2>Security is concern</h2>

<p>We collect users private data, it was obvioulsy just impossible to give a chance of someone else access it. So, have to secure the application with SSL connection, so all trafic between API and browser is crypted. SSL became a quite hard, first because certificate is rather expensive, second you have to install on server, which I never did before.</p>

<p>The importance of SSL left us with a no-go on <a href="https://www.nodejitsu.com/">Nodejitsu</a>. Nodejitsu policies allows to have SSL connections only on &ldquo;Bussiness Plan&rdquo;, which costs 120USD/month. That was not that money we ready to put on table. We had to have change the way we host application. Basically, it meant &ndash; move out from PaaS to IaaS, and do all the stuff on your own.</p>

<p>I personally felt bad about, since we&rsquo;ve really get used to PaaS. But, we&rsquo;ve found a way around, having place own application on <a href="https://www.digitalocean.com/">Digital Ocean</a> cloud, in conjunction with <a href="https://github.com/progrium/dokku">dokku</a>, which allows us to Heroku-like deployment model. That also gave me the chance to play vagrant/linux/docker more that I could ever image. I contributed <a href="https://github.com/progrium/dokku">dokku</a> some important stuff as SSL and ENV support and that gave ability to use it for production needs.</p>

<h2>Current technology stack</h2>

<p>So, a little bit of geeky info. We running on:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.digitalocean.com/">Digital Ocean</a>, 2 droplets one for staging and one for production</li>
<li><a href="http://nginx.org/">Nginx</a> 1.4, ssl, routing and balancing 2 Node.js servers on each droplet</li>
<li><a href="http://nodejs.org/">Node.js</a> 0.8.25 + <a href="http://expressjs.com/">Express.js</a> based API</li>
<li><a href="http://www.mongohq.com/home">MongoHQ</a> deplyment for staging and production database</li>
<li>Each Node.js server runs in <a href="http://www.docker.io/">docker</a> container</li>
<li>Deployments and docker orchestration by <a href="https://github.com/progrium/dokku">dokku</a></li>
<li><a href="http://angularjs.org/">AngularJS</a> driven client</li>
<li>Handcrafted CSS, HTML (no frameworks)</li>
</ul>


<p>Each of these is very interesting and demands dedicated posts. Hope, we do some in future.</p>

<h2>Conclusions</h2>

<p>Just current results: 18 hours after, we have 40 users, 62 network connections, 10861 item collected. That&rsquo;s the motivating stuff, so we feel very positive to carry that on.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
