<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: changes | Alexander Beletsky's development blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://beletsky.net/blog/categories/changes/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://beletsky.net/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-04T18:31:52+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://beletsky.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alexander Beletsky]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[alexander.beletsky@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I Quit My Job]]></title>
    <link href="http://beletsky.net/2013/12/i-quit-my-job.html"/>
    <updated>2013-12-09T16:20:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://beletsky.net/2013/12/i-quit-my-job</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since 6 Dec 2013, I&rsquo;m officially unemployed. I quit my job in E-conomic there I <a href="http://beletsky.net/blog/categories/e-conomic/">spent almost 3.5 years</a> of happy life. Leaving the company was a really tough decision, but it had to be made.</p>

<p>A lot of things happed during that time. No doubts, E-conomic and Ciklum did the most significant impact of my professional career so far. The reason for that is simple: the people surrounds you are most important aspect in your job. From the very first days, till last ones &ndash; I worked with high qualified professionals there.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>For all the period I felt the passion towards what I&rsquo;m doing. Doesn&rsquo;t matter, is that .NET or JavaScript, new features or bug fixes. Everything made sense to me. I like to see how company improved through the time and I want to believe I was the part of that improvements.</p>

<p>We worked really hard there and solved hard problems. We had shitty situations and big celebrations. We had long debates and small dramas. We had fun.</p>

<p>But for a last couple of months, I realized that something has changed. That feeling could be called &ndash; <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BPlsqo2bk2M">Thrill is gone</a>.</p>

<p>Yes, simply enough. I can&rsquo;t work on anything if I&rsquo;m not 100% excited about. The product we worked on already become big and well established. Even with new features there I haven&rsquo;t seen big challenges to me. Every day was a kind of &ldquo;another day in a office&rdquo;, not like &ldquo;climbing to Kilimanjaro&rdquo;, that I prefer to feel from work.</p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t get me wrong. I think any project could be challenging and all the time it&rsquo;s possible to find a challenge, but I clearly realized &ndash; to be honest to yourself and your company, you have to move on.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not leaving for competitor, I&rsquo;m not leaving for money, I&rsquo;m not leaving for better place. Instead, I&rsquo;m putting myself outside the comfort zone and I want to challenge myself as hard as possible. I quit my job, to do something completely new to me.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
