<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: digitalocean | Alexander Beletsky's development blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://beletsky.net/blog/categories/digitalocean/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://beletsky.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-01T15:28:25+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://beletsky.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alexander Beletsky]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[alexander.beletsky@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Digital Ocean + Dokku = 10$ Heroku]]></title>
    <link href="http://beletsky.net/2013/08/digitalocean-plus-dokku-equals-10-heroku.html"/>
    <updated>2013-08-28T22:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://beletsky.net/2013/08/digitalocean-plus-dokku-equals-10-heroku</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My last infrastructure related <a href="http://beletsky.net/2013/07/why-we-moved-from-appfog-to-nodejitsu.html">post</a> was about an experience of using AppFog and switching to Nodejitsu eventually. But that was not the end. In short: for <a href="https://likeastore.com/">Likeastore</a> we needed SSL support, it happed that SSL is only available for Nodejitsu business plan, which price is 120 USD. That was simply to much for our small venture.</p>

<p>Long time ago, I realized &ndash; constrains are good. This case just proved that. Looking for alternative options, gave really nice results, which I easily could be re-used if you looking for simple deployment solutions.</p>

<!-- More -->


<h2>Heroku</h2>

<p>Heroku is good service. Afraid to be mistaken, but that&rsquo;s probably Heroku who popularized &ldquo;git-powered&rdquo; deployments much, ones there deployment script looks like:</p>

<p>```bash</p>

<blockquote><p>git push heroku master
```</p></blockquote>

<p>The rest is all about the service &ndash; prepare runtime, deploy code, start web application etc. Besides of that Heroku open-sourced a lot of good stuff, including so called <a href="https://devcenter.heroku.com/articles/buildpacks">buildpacks</a>, some ready to use scripts that are able to setup the dyno with all required runtime to be able to start application there.</p>

<p>I never seriously used Heroku, though. What I dislike, is pricing. Also, the other people I asked about their satisfaction of using Heroku, was not satisfying much (arguable). We needed more lightweight, easy to change setup.</p>

<h2>Digital Ocean</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.digitalocean.com/?refcode=de56d081b272">Digital Ocean</a> is very fast growing cloud-computing service. It&rsquo;s not PaaS (platform as a service) like Heroku, it&rsquo;s rather IaaS (infrastructure as a service). They are notable for few major things:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Pricing</strong> &ndash; really (mean, really!) competitive pricing, 1GB RAM, 30GB SSD machine for 10$.</li>
<li><strong>Easy of use</strong> &ndash; the flow from registration for first droplet creation is smooth and clear.</li>
<li><strong>Regions</strong> &ndash; machines can be fired up for both US and EU, ideal for us.</li>
</ul>


<p>But again, Digital Ocean is nothing more as great infrastructure. Herding the server is all up to you. I personally was really afraid of that perspective of setting up nginx, configuring firewalls, load-balancing etc., that prevented me to look to Digital Ocean closely. Getting used to deployment procedures with Nodejitsu and Heroku, it&rsquo;s real pain to deploy app by FTP again and do everything manually.</p>

<p>But lucky chance I noticed <a href="https://github.com/progrium/dokku">Dokku</a> project and that was something really great, explain why later.</p>

<h2>Dokku &amp; Docker</h2>

<p>So, <a href="https://github.com/progrium/dokku">Dokku</a> is simply amazing hack (or more correctly, combination of diffrent hacks) by <a href="https://github.com/progrium">Jeff Lindsay</a>. Some initial facts:</p>

<ul>
<li>Written in Shell script and currently nearly 100 lines of code</li>
<li>Based on Docker</li>
<li>Provides Heroku-like deployment experience</li>
<li>Community-driven</li>
</ul>


<p>Dokku, can be installed to Ubuntu 13 machine and turn that machine into Heroku-like server. I mean, you can push the code there and Dokku, will fire-up new <em>docker process</em>, deploy code there, start the application, configure nginx and setup environment variables and SSL.</p>

<p>Btw, the time I just looked to Dokku, they missed exactly support of ENV variables and SSL. It was not acceptable for me, without those 2 features. Constraints again, but that gave me ability to contribute the projects and eventually I submitted both features.</p>

<p>Dokku, is very interesting project. First of all, because it based on trendy <a href="http://www.docker.io/">Docker</a>. Docker is &ldquo;Virtual-Machine-Based-Deployment&rdquo; alternative. Deployment on virtual boxes are de-facto standard now and docker is about to change that. Guys from <a href="https://www.dotcloud.com/">dotCloud</a> open-sourced solution that allows to run isolated processes (containers) &ndash; that are like lightweight virtual machines. You can deploy docker on Ubuntu server and then use that as host any kind of applications or databases.</p>

<p>Docker could turn Ubuntu Server to PaaS and Dokku makes great &ldquo;interface&rdquo; for that.</p>

<p>Each Dokku piece is very interesting indeed and I hope to blog more about. And Dokku is using Heroku buildbacks, which makes you feel you deal with Heroku, not with your own setup.</p>

<h2>Putting Things Together</h2>

<p>Digital Ocean and Dokku make a perfect match. As I said above, Digital Ocean is something you can really start quick with. So, what we did is just started up 10$ Ubuntu 13 server and installed Dokku there. In total it took 7 minutes or so. I would not bother you with instructions, cause you find a lot in <a href="https://medium.com/code-adventures/438bce155dcb">internet</a>.. but also, assuming that DO + Dokku is a kind of Apple product, that does not require instructions.</p>

<p>First impression was simply amazing. You have everything under control and fill great with &ldquo;git-powered&rdquo; deployments. So, after successful try that machine became our staging server and I also fired-up another one for production one.</p>

<p>Now, then we developing features and what to show each other or test, you just need to do following:</p>

<p>```bash</p>

<blockquote><p>git push deploy-staging feature:master
Counting objects: 7, done.
Delta compression using up to 8 threads.
Compressing objects: 100% (4/4), done.
Writing objects: 100% (4/4), 445 bytes | 0 bytes/s, done.
Total 4 (delta 2), reused 0 (delta 0)
remote: &mdash;&mdash;&ndash;> Building collector &hellip;
remote:        Node.js app detected
remote: &mdash;&mdash;&ndash;> Resolving engine versions
remote:        Using Node.js version: 0.10.15
remote:        Using npm version: 1.2.30
remote: &mdash;&mdash;&ndash;> Fetching Node.js binaries
remote: &mdash;&mdash;&ndash;> Vendoring node into slug
remote: &mdash;&mdash;&ndash;> Installing dependencies with npm
remote:        npm WARN package.json <a href="&#x6d;&#97;&#105;&#108;&#x74;&#x6f;&#x3a;&#x6c;&#105;&#x6b;&#x65;&#97;&#115;&#116;&#x6f;&#x72;&#101;&#45;&#x63;&#x6f;&#108;&#108;&#101;&#99;&#116;&#111;&#114;&#64;&#x30;&#x2e;&#48;&#x2e;&#x32;&#x2d;&#x32;&#x31;">&#108;&#105;&#107;&#101;&#97;&#x73;&#x74;&#111;&#114;&#101;&#x2d;&#99;&#111;&#108;&#x6c;&#101;&#x63;&#x74;&#111;&#x72;&#64;&#48;&#46;&#x30;&#x2e;&#50;&#45;&#x32;&#x31;</a> No repository field.
remote:        npm http GET <a href="https://registry.npmjs.org/mongojs">https://registry.npmjs.org/mongojs</a>
remote:        npm http GET <a href="https://registry.npmjs.org/underscore">https://registry.npmjs.org/underscore</a></p></blockquote>

<p>&hellip;</p>

<p>remote: =====> Application deployed:
remote:        <a href="http://stage-collector.likeastore.com">http://stage-collector.likeastore.com</a>
```</p>

<p>The time we are ready to release:</p>

<p>```bash</p>

<blockquote><p>git push deploy-production master
Counting objects: 7, done.
Delta compression using up to 8 threads.
&hellip;</p></blockquote>

<p>remote: =====> Application deployed:
remote:        <a href="http://collector.likeastore.com">http://collector.likeastore.com</a>
```</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s fast and it&rsquo;s pretty reliable.</p>

<p>For conclusion, I would say that using both Digial Ocean and Dokku was a clear win for <a href="https://likeastore.com/">Likeastore</a> being released.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
